hey welcome to week four of Brandon
sanderson's writing lectures the 2025
Edition I'm taking questions from the
audience this time but you weren't there
in that audience I'd like to give you a
chance so if you watch this video and
have questions about plot do try to
watch the previous two as well uh but if
you've been following along and I don't
get to answering your question that you
might have leave it in the comments I'm
going to do a special webon
uh Q&A for you guys so post your
questions here in the comments about
plot best if you can reference the
previous two lectures or things I talk
in this um and I will do my best to get
to you and for now enjoy Q&A on plot all
right everybody Welcome to writing
science fiction fantasy the Q&A
yeah so I have in my hand
the questions that you have asked about
plot and I'm going to get to some of
them because most likely I will answer
one or two of these and then you will
start raising your hands and I will get
sidetracked by answering the questions
you all have here but let's see all
right so besides tone promises what are
some of the most important kinds of
promises to make this is an excellent
question um because I really focused on
the tone promises but there's a lot more
going on here you do
generally want to try to promise what
kind of plot it's going to be Little P
plot right um You don't have to promise
big p plot
until near the end of act one if you
think that way sometimes you just do
right again we reference star I
reference Star Wars a lot because it's a
movie that everybody has seen and that
breaks down really well it promises it
in scene one big ship little ship big
ship's dominating little ship it's about
the little ship blowing up the big
ship ah yeah um so right Star Wars does
a lot of things like that that uh that
really just kind of Click into place so
um you can make a promise about your big
p plot but also you know you can do it
Little P plot you can make a character
promise uh the original Mulan is really
good at this the Disney Mulan right this
is a character promise how does Mulan
solve problems she solves problems in a
smart way if you don't remember the
opening of that she has to feed the
chickens I believe it is and so she like
ties the feed um to a dog and then has
the dog go running and feed the animals
right this is a kind of this is the sort
of character that we're doing she is
going to solve problems in an
unconventional way uh using her wits um
and and indeed that is basically who
Mulan is all the way through you can
give a promise of a character Arc like
who is this character what do they want
um what are they going to change and
become I do think that
um again these can be at the beginning
they don't have to be but you usually
want to promise a character Arc you
usually want to promise like every
Disney movie ever has an I want song
Right This is the the journey they're
going to go on and what they want to get
and who they are blah blah blah blah
blah right um one of the things that uh
you can also promise is you can
promise if you do it right what your
standup and cheer moment is going to
be um and that can be really handy for
helping people get you know put up
sometimes with the character getting
beaten down because they know each of
those times the character is be getting
beaten down it is set up for that moment
where they will be victorious um this
usually involves um you know like let's
use the original Captain America right
Captain America is a spindly little guy
who can't fight he still tries to
protect people and gets into fights and
his friend has to bail him out you know
what kind of movie you're watching
you know you're there for a superhero
transformation that is a promise he is
eventually going to be able to be the
strong one and save his friend right um
and so that is a promise of you know
your character's transformation but
really it's like foreshadowing you're
going to have a moment where you get a
stand up and cheer for this guy it's
coming you got to put up with him you
know um be in a SP spindly dweeb for
little while uh but then after that he's
going to you know the the the heart is
more important than the body um and that
sort of stuff so all of those are types
of promises you can make down to the
classic check offs gun right the classic
check offs gun this is a story writing
adage that says if you hang a gun on the
gun on the wall and or on the m above
the mantle um or on the mantle if you
hang a gun up if you show a gun in act
one you should fire that before the end
of the movie is basically what I'm
paraphrasing they he uses it more
explicitly than that but the idea is
that people are going to expect if you
see and highlight something as a writer
that that thing will be important or
relevant you can use that against them
if you would like uh you can you can use
those as red herrings for setups and a
different kind of payoff where it's like
you thought you knew what was happening
you don't but just promises are what
make people engage with a story your
progress is what keeps them there your
payoff is what honestly is going to make
them read the next book right A lot of
people will read a book with bad payoff
and they'll get to the
end they're generally not going to put
the book down because of bad payoff what
they're going to do is go ride a one
star or even worse the two stars the two
stars are the worst right that's when
you really want to get an author you
leave the two star cuz the onear STS
they're just like I didn't finish this
it wasn't for me right the two stars are
like oh this could have been good but it
screwed up the ending um
so so yeah um the the two stars are
always like I wanted to like this but
the author sucks um
so uh what do you do if you feel your
plot is too
unoriginal uh another good question um
so
if you are worried you're too
unoriginal most of the time you should
stop Str stressing about this all right
artists love to stress about being
unoriginal your originality will almost
certainly come out as a natural growth
of you progressing and writing as a
Storyteller usually
I'm going to give you the reason why
it's usually in a minute but usually
this isn't as big a problem as you think
it
is once in a while it kind of is um this
is if early readers are telling you your
books to derivative uh if consistently
you write books that feel a little bit
derivative sometimes you can just be
like well I am a product of my
Inspirations I don't know
that James Cameron really cares that
much that people call Avatar dances with
Smurfs
right he made the movie he wanted to
make he loves his own movie people love
that movie he got a theme park and you
know made a billion dollars um so but if
this does bother you and if you are
consistently getting it and you are
established right this isn't your first
book you've practiced and later on
you're like this book is too unoriginal
there's a number of things that you can
do number one is play off the fact that
people are expecting certain things and
force yourself to take the next step say
all right what the story would normally
do here is X it's been done that way
over and
over what can I
do that will make my story deeper and
more interesting by making a different
decision example uh Stormlight
Archive one of the big problems I had
with way of Kings Prime uh which you can
read for free if you want to do so for
uh study purposes I don't think it's
that good uh but people seem to enjoy
reading it anyway this is the version I
wrote in 2002 a lot of the book worked
but the character that was in the place
of kaledin did not in this book I had a
pretty standard plot line young Spearman
saves the king or the king's brother um
earns himself a Knighthood and it's a
story of him learning to navigate the
Upper Crust of society you can do that
very well it's a that can be a very
interesting story but I as an author at
the end of the book I'm like that is not
who I want this character to be even
though I wrote the whole book feels like
he's the most Bland person in the entire
story and we're seeing the majority of
it through his eyes something is wrong
this is a case where I felt like my plot
was UN original if you've read the way
of Kings I'll try not to give uh too big
of spoilers if you haven't but the
entire revision of that um that story
which kind of took it a completely
different direction was me saying okay
what if a character makes the opposite
decision that most people would make why
would that be a better story how can I
make that earned for his character and
how can I make the story really work
because of
it don't twist for twists
sake okay twist because it makes your
story
better anyone can surprise a reader you
have a character open the door and get
shot and then it's over and you end like
it's not hard to surprise readers it
really
isn't surprising them affect ly in a way
that makes your story more interesting
that they that it something happens
they're like the story is better now
that this twist has happened that's hard
okay so if your story doesn't need a
Twist don't feel bad not having a Twist
Pride and Prejudice is not worse because
they get together at the end
spoilers
right but that doesn't mean you couldn't
if you are kind of Board of that
narrative say well what am I going to do
differently my one warning to you on
this is I warn you to foreshadow early
it's going to be a different kind of
story yes into the woods gets away with
not doing so to the extent that I
recommend people do you can not
foreshadow you can turn your story into
something else in the middle but be
warned I tell a story sometimes about an
author who broke in around the same time
I did and my U books really started to
take off and his um didn't take off to
the same extent we met once very nice
person I'm not going to mention who it
is because I've told this story so many
times it's been 20 years and I don't
even remember know if I'm remembering
the details right all right this is what
happens to you but I remember meeting
this author and I had started reading
their book and their book was good but
it wasn't for me I'd read a bunch of
traditional Quest fantasy when I was
younger and I was kind of done with
young person um finds out their air to
the throne and chases a magical object
um uh that the book you know like that
they they're looking to get because then
they can use the magical object to save
the day not saying that I won't someday
read another book like that that just
blows my mind and I love um but at that
point I was kind of done with the Terry
Brooks Style of book and I I told him
that I'm like you know I tried the book
you're obviously a good writer it just
wasn't for me he's like why I'm like
well this and this he's like you know I
got that so many times in my reviews but
the thing is at the 3/4 Mark I I twisted
on its head and that's not the case of
what the book is at all in fact I wrote
the book he said to be a
deconstruction of that archetype that
was so popular and I it it's really
frustrating that I then get uh people
not liking the book because of the very
thing I was deconstructing the people
that he thought would love his book were
complaining I don't know if this my
interpretation is correct but what I
feel might be the lesson here is
that if your book is going to have a
revolution that big that is
danger the people who are looking for a
classic um ya style Quest fantasy what's
going to happen to them when they get to
the three4 mark they're mad they're mad
right they're like wait a minute you're
deconstructing the thing that I love and
saying it's not
cool yeah they're mad right um what
about the people who would love a
deconstruction of the quest fantasy they
get that get there because like myself
they put the book down in the first
third because they're like well you know
this this isn't targeted at me um isn't
again to say that you can't do this but
your promises can indicate that this is
a book that is heading that direction
and it is hard to do hard things to do
often fortun you to grows are writer so
I do encourage you to to try them but
you know that's my warning to you on
that one be careful about that if that's
the story you want to tell try to figure
out how you're going to get the Right
audience to that
book um and not have them put it down
you know and early chapters one way to
do that might be to write other books
that are more explicitly deconstructions
so that when you're popular and you
release this one everyone's like ah this
reads like a standard Quest
fantasy I know you uh author person I
know where this is going I'm going to
enjoy this real big when that kid who
finds a magic sword you know turns out
to be a demon and destroyed by it and we
deconstruct everything and suddenly it's
like whatever right um
so so yeah um there's my answer to you
on that one if you feel your plot is um
is
unoriginal push yourself harder is
answer number one uh number two
transpose that plot to a new uh genre
and or a sub new subg genre and try to
use the new sub genre's tropes to impact
the story in interesting ways this is
the 10 Things I Hate About You
methodology right the Shakespeare
retelling um you know taking a story and
putting it in a new setting and then
asking yourself all right with these new
genre conventions what do we do to this
kind of story you can always often ask
yourself all right the standard story um
what are the flaws in this story how can
we make a story about those flaws
mistborn exists because I was reading
Harry
Potter and I said man these dark Lords
never get a break right they always get
killed by some kid or there's like a
furry footed British dude who throws the
ring in a hole like you were the most
powerful thing around and then oh sorry
you were destroyed by the power of a
mother's love
right right like what if the dark lord
won what if froto got to the end and
Son's like my ring I lost
that thanks for bringing it back it must
have been really hard to do uh anyway
you're dead and I take over the world
right like that was the inspiration
originally for MB um you can you know
reverse this story on its head and the
the secret is a lot of stories that
reverse on their head a lot of
deconstructionism will tell you what is
it you're relying on what you're denying
um you will need to be using those same
narrative tropes just in interesting
ways in order to actually deconstruct in
a lot of uh at least popular fiction
methodology so you will be able to have
your cake and eat it too which is the
big Dark Secret of deconstructionist ism
as it applies to uh to writing popular
fiction um so yeah uh anyway uh yeah
question over there uh for law of us
writing our first books um I'd love to
write a book and have a big series and
have it going forever but for those
books promises that are unfulfilled in
that book yeah when your first time no
no or okay good question so you're
writing a big series um you want to have
it go on for a long time what are the
promises that you are going to leave
unfulfilled is that a no no the answer
is you can definitely leave some
promises unfulfilled right uh depends on
how you do it if we go back to Star Wars
Darth Vader being defeated is like a Min
promise fulfilled but not a big promise
fulfilled and you're they're able to you
know get away with that uh Lord of the
Rings it's like the promise is we're
going to we're going to destroy the ring
we don't do that in book One spoilers um
right and so basically readers will
accept if you are fulfilling some
promises and putting off others right
what is fellowship the ring fulfill on
the ring will corrupt those who are
around it that's really cool it's a good
fulfilling sort of thing to that end and
the fellowship then breaks and yada yada
so what I do recommend is don't save all
the cool stuff for book
Seven new writers run into this I'm I'm
exaggerating but they'll be like this
will get really cool once I do X Y and Z
well for your first novels make sure the
really cool is there right at the start
um don't make people wait to find out if
you can tell a good ending this is why
in general there's exceptions to every
rule in general all things being equal I
recommend that new writers trying to
break in tell a complete story with SQL
potential in their first
book I like to do this
when I can even as an established author
Skyward is a complete story at the end
we say this is where it's going to go
for the series but the first book stands
very well its own steelart is a complete
story mistborn is a complete story um I
tend to do this with series Stormlight
is not so much one right and I try to
kind of make that uh promise but if you
are looking at the plot ARS of
Stormlight we do not get into solving
the problem of the capital P plot of the
series but the story of the bridge
cruise that we promise is fulfilled so
you give a really powerful fulfillment
to a primary character's Arc and then
leave greater things unanswered and
you're fine the other way of course is
to do it is to do something that is a um
is a more serialized series uh I know
that sounds odd but you know uh one
where each book is going to have its own
complete Arc and can be read out of
order um the those sorts of stories
don't have this problem obviously but if
you're wanting to do the big epic that's
what I recommend go ahead we talked last
week about different plotting methods
yes say you're just starting a project
from
scratch getting started your story but
you're try to figure out which plotting
method best your specific you have any
advice on approach yeah advice on
approaching um if you want to try
different plotting methods uh matching
them to a given story
uh it's going to be really individual to
you uh what have you tried in the past
and what has worked for you in the past
take what is worked if you're a new
author meaning you've you haven't
written your sixth book yet is what I
would uh put as a newer author right um
at that point it's like all right what
worked in the past I'm going to lean
into this and do it even more does it
work better if I lean in even more um
does it not work if if you're also a new
writer like you may want to try the um
Whose Line Is It Is It Anyway version of
writing a story where it's like I know
I'm going to do this this and this go
and I don't know what any chapter is
going to be and you know you yes but no
and uh that sort of stuff uh your way
through an entire book um the alcatra
books were written that way uh I would
brainstorm a bunch of things just like
uh Whose Line Is It Anyway and say these
all have to go in the book by the end uh
go and I would not outline uh because I
wanted to practice Discovery writing and
things like that so if you wonder where
the alra books came from that will not
surprise any of you who have read them
um where those books where those books
come from uh practicing the different
methodologies is just handy for many
authors as a tool but do also understand
there are a lot of authors who find one
way of writing a story that really works
for them and they lean into it and they
don't change for the next 60 years and
they write classic after Classic so uh
don't stress if you're not the type
that's like I want to try all these if
you have something that works just do it
uh what would I do like I'd try the two
extremes and then try to work my way uh
into something that is a mix of them
since most people I know are a mix the
two streams being you know Whose Line is
it any way yourself your way through an
entire book um and and also World
Builder disease you give yourself like
you know 4 months depending on whatever
and you just won't let yourself right uh
only do this once those of you who spend
20 years don't do that but you know give
yourself a deadline but a really liberal
one and World build disease and plot and
then see if that makes your book better
or not yeah um when you're running
overlapping story arcs how do you plan
it so that everything all the arcs come
together in that perfect stand of and
cheer moment overlapping uh arcs how do
you work them together so they come
together in a standup and cheer moment
uh a few tips number one is um you may
not get it right in the first draft you
may not get it right in the fifth draft
you will hopefully eventually get it
right uh but a few tips one of the
things that tends to stand up and cheer
is when you can hit the um character
arcs uh emotional payoff right before
the uh the kind of phys IAL Arc the
external Arc internal then external
usually is the beat that you want right
Han comes back and saves Luke Luke
decides to be a Jedi and Trust in the
force then they defeat um the uh the bad
guys because they have both made their
decisions that's your standard you can
reverse it but that's just kind of a
rule of thumb if you can use that that
internal Arc to then push you into the
external Arc um give them the last
little bit they need those are generally
stand up and cheer moments the reason
being that if you force out it way well
the reader is waiting the reader is
waiting the viewer in this case for Han
to come back and the viewer is waiting
for Luke to decide to be a Jedi these
are the two things that you've just been
watching them both fail at repeatedly
but you know they're both getting close
then because they succeed they did it it
isn't that the narrative just came
together it's that they
struggled
failed made uh impactful decisions and
those impactful decisions made them
succeed that's usually what we talk
about when with stand up and cheer um
right um there are things you're waiting
for you can do them without as much
character Arc you can do them by just
punishing the character right so much
that when uh mild spoilers when they
when the hammer hits their hand you
cheer because they've been through so
much right when they're able to wield
Thor's hammer um that's you know they've
struggled so much it's time to have a
success um if you are balancing a whole
bunch of plot lines another rule of
thumb
is you can't overlap them too much to
the point that the reader gets a sort
of
paralysis to awesome things happening a
numbness a numbness to awesome things
happening whereas if you stagger those
sometimes that better is better as
sander lanch generally actually tries to
stagger them it depends on the book so
that they're coming in order but even a
sander lanch like I can go too far um
I've had to trim back books before um
and in in revisions because there's too
many twists too many things becoming uh
fulfilled and sometimes you back up and
say I'm going to use this as the kind of
a climactic moment at the two3 Mark for
this character then they're going to
fade into the background and then we can
uh then we can focus on the big thing I
did that a ton in The Wheel of Time
where it's like all right midpoint
climax it feels like an ending but for
this minor character you are now allowed
as a reader to be like that was awesome
they're cool now they won't distract me
from Rand anymore uh pat on the head off
into the uh to the to the mist of time
for you thank you for you know uh right
like that sort of thing can be really
handy to do also uh so few things there
let me get one more of these and then
we'll do some more questions uh from the
audience so all right because these are
all really good
questions um what are some common
mistakes made when it comes to
Exposition oh Exposition oh Exposition
so one of the things so if you don't
know what Exposition means um in a story
particularly a Science Fiction and
Fantasy story you are going to have to
as a writer bring the reader up to speed
on a ton of things we call this a
learning curve every story has a
learning curve
the more sci-fi fantasy-ish it is the
steeper your learning curve because the
higher the more you're going to have to
learn to be brought up to speed if you
are reading a story about a student at
BYU who is taking a science fiction
fantasy class and trying to write their
first
novel your learning curve the point that
you have to get to is not so high the
amount you have to learn you already
know all of this you as a reader now
someone from another country um who has
never heard of this might have a steeper
learning curve so you can't make it
perfect for every reader but understand
that right historicals tend to have a
steeper learning curve uh things that
are very narrow in a genre tend to have
a steeper learning curve because you can
rely on other things other books the
reader has read and sci-fi fantasy tends
to have a steeper learning curve you can
make the learning curve more shallow by
not frontloading exposition
and by using Exposition well Exposition
what when we use classic Exposition it
is when the reader uh the character
basically either in first person or in
third person gives a big paragraph
explaining well the gods were like this
and they did this so that we have this
so that we have this now this and the
magic works like this and blah you know
all of this stuff you generally want as
a writer to do everything you can to to
make your learning curve more
shallow without impacting the sub genre
and art that you're trying to make right
shallow learning curves good unless they
inhibit the story you're trying to tell
Stephen Erikson the story he's trying to
tell did not benefit from a shallower
learning curve because that was part of
the point uh way of Kings has a steeper
learning curve than mistborn and so
don't frontload your exposition uh Gone
are the days where you would write a
prologue that is a huge Exposition dump
uh you can still find plenty of fine
fantasy novels from the 70s and 80s that
do that um
and gone are the days when you can get
away with giant info dumps is what we
call them in your opening chapters move
them out into dialogue where you can but
be careful about Maiden Butler dialogue
this is kind of a a term we borrow from
uh from the stage world where you know
you would have the maiden Butler come on
the the the start of a play and be like
as you know the lady is away for the
weekend and the other's like yes and as
you know the you know the master now
will go golfing because she hates his
golfing habit you know well and as you
know he's been getting you want to avoid
they also call you it as you know Bob uh
dialogue
so how do you do this right how do you
write it um so moving it to dialogue
will naturally make the learning curve a
little easier making it part of
something important to the characters
that you get across briefly uh will make
it will make your learning curve a
little shallow it's easier to read if
it's important to the characters if it's
in dialogue or uh these sorts of things
I often say the grand skill of writing
sci-fi f
FY is to be able to get your exposition
to readers without them realizing that
you're
expositing my wife when my kids were
younger would make for them a smoothie
every
morning
right she would put spinach in the
smoothie and say this is making it into
zombie guts my kids were like Calvin
from Calvin and Hobs right zombie guts
equals good and
tasty and they're like wow zombie guts
she would do this in order to get them
to eat something that has a least a
little bit of vitamin in it right um you
want your exposition to be the uh the
spinach and the reader smoothie you want
them to not realize that it's happening
and you do this by avoiding the big
paragraphs by putting in only what you
need particularly at the beginning don't
feel you need to dump everything uh I
will get to you hands down for now it's
it's actually kind of distracting so um
so try not to
um try not
to get them bored try to make it
meaningful and important and useful to
the narrative uh try to slip it in align
here between dialogue I line in the
dialogue uh try to come up with reasons
to construct scenes where these things
are relevant you know there are dwarves
and wizards in The Hobbit because
they're coming and eating all of Bilbo's
food and Bilbo is so annoyed that
they're eating his food that scene tells
you who billbo is that it's a world fall
of dwarves and wizards uh that this
guy's a homebody and through their
natural conversation you find out
they're on a big adventure you don't
need the Deep Exposition you don't need
to know um the nature of the one ring in
order to have Bilbo be annoyed that
dwarves are at uh his door even if the
nature of the one ring is your capital P
plot it wasn't even when he wrote The
Hobbit do you guys know he went back and
revised The Hobbit to change the thing
with the One Ring after he decided to
write Lord of the
Rings I would call that cheating but
it's not cuz Grandpa tolken did it which
means we all can yeah he released The
Hobbit then he's like oh wow um as I've
decided what the one ring is Gollum
probably shouldn't just not care about
it i' better revise The Hobbit to make
the One Ring more uh more relevant to
what the one ring is so anyway all right
I got you all right so I was wondering
like if you have a huge like a lot of
expedition Expedition it' be super
steeping curb would spending like
changing how long it takes to get that
out so like extending it with that
shorten the curve by like teaching them
interested to okay learn more about it
and with that pulled it Forward yeah one
more time I think I've got what you're
asking okay I
can't so if you have like what would be
a lot of content to like have a huge
steep you're going to have a steep
learning C you got a lot of content is
it better to expand that to let them
okay good question this is this is an
excellent question
so you can do that it's dangerous
because longer can be more boring right
uh I would counter with it depends on
your
subgenre if you're writing in middle
grade it is very traditional to lengthen
out that learning curve by starting kid
in our world here are their problems
learn their problems and their friends
before pulled into a fantasy world now
those problems and Friends uh you
understand and we can start on the
fantasy world why portal fantasy tends
to be uh consistently the most popular
middle grade uh variety of uh fantasy
because you can establish some stakes
and some character before a lot of Epic
Fantasy just like no we're starting
right in boom someone's getting attacked
um steeper learning curve because you're
audience will accept it and also it's
the art you want to tell like I said
earlier so yes you can do that
often you don't want to lengthen it too
much but if you can construct that
perfect scene that perfect scene that
can show character and the problem and
hint at some of the important things of
the world and inject that into the
beginning of your story that can often
it does make your story a little longer
but it can shallow out that learning or
yes shallow whatever it can even out
that learning curve but it can also let
you hit character really hard first off
then you can start adding things as they
go along so one of the reasons why Quest
fantasies so often are start in a city
or town that feels a awful lot like
Rural
America um so that everybody who was
reading Old Yeller and Where the Red
Fern grow and things like that at the at
the time these were popular is like all
right I'm grounded I'm grounded in
Randal Thor and he you know he lives on
a farm with his dad and he's thinks
there's a girl in town that's cute that
he might want to to marry but he doesn't
want to have to quite make those
decisions yet he's glad he's got his dad
he wishes he knew his mom monsters right
and then out of that world into a
fantasy world it's not a portal fantasy
technically but you can see how it's
like one half a portal fantasy same with
uh with Lord of the Rings uh same with a
lot of this Quest fantasy we don't have
to do that as much anymore because we
can rely on people knowing what a
fantasy world was when tolken wrote like
f what a fantasy world was was a little
more nebulous to the general public um
in fact I haven't yet been able to
identify and someday I would like to see
if we can find the the definitive first
fantasy novel that doesn't reference our
world in any
way because I thought for a while it
might be Lord of the Rings but it's
really not because he
said Lord of the Rings is a prehistory
to earth right um and so what is the
first one the the at least first one
that's you know that's that people
actually read maybe there's something
some manuscript somebody wrote but you
know what I mean I'm still trying to
find that one uh but basically all
fantasy as a rule until around tolken
referenced Earth in some way they even
usually used it in the title right Earth
sea um in order to just help with that
learning curve and we don't have to do
that as much anymore which is which is
nice um and I I kind of say the rise of
uh nerd culture being just popular
culture has helped that people
understand this is a fantasy book I
understand what a fantasy book is uh
that's really big I'll read the shorter
ones about people kissing um but I don't
mind that people read the shorter ones
about people kissing because some of
those also say well maybe I I like that
big one now so thank you for everyone
who's writing the fantasy books about
people kissing um all right uh there are
some other questions go so when you have
a book that's a lot of promises how do
you like keep track of that as you write
what organizational method can you use
make your Mak yeah what organization can
you use I just have an outline right um
in fact I should I should do this
because I didn't do it uh last time uh
what do I do how do I actually build an
outline so the Sanderson method of
building an
outline I sit down with my story and I
start
identifying what my different plot
Cycles are all of the small p+ usually
I'm going to want one for each
character
one right I'm going to want an internal
Arc for them in some way most stories uh
benefit from a character's internal
Journey um this is the you know struggle
to overcome X Y or Z or to become X Y or
Z or something like that I'm usually
going to want one of uh a some of those
but I'm also going to be like all right
uh the main sort of plot uh that I'm
going to be doing promises for or
progress um I'm going be like all right
what's what's the big one what is what
is happening in this story um and this
might be something like all right
kaladin needs to save a bridge crew this
is the kind of Promise He makes himself
in chapter whatever 11 or 12 or wherever
it is where he's like I'm going to try
one more time and this time I'm going to
actually save somebody right that
becomes kind of a major like this is the
spine I'm hanging my story on for a book
as big as the way of Kings I will
probably have three of these there'll be
kind of one main one and then two
submain ones so um kind of this is like
uh external
plot and I'll usually at the same time
have some character
interactions um like I might have a
romance uh and I might have an
information
plot right a lot of um my books it's
like how does the magic work um right
right in way of Kings it's less there is
an info plot but the info plot is with
Shalon uh with kaladin it's not an info
plot it's an apprentice plot except he
has no master to teach him um but it's
that sort of plot it's like I need to
work this out and become a master of
this otherwise everybody I love is going
to die um and so I identify what these
things are and I start writing down what
are my progress what are my big moments
of progress usually I start at the end
what's my stand up and cheer if there is
or what's the kind of ultimate
culmination of this and this and this
and this and this and this and this uh
and I identify all of these things and I
start putting bullet points and
brainstorming what are my steps along
the way what are signposts I know what
each of these endings
is um how can I
indicate that we're making progress what
are the places where they backslide what
are the big moments where you know you
think it's not going to work that is
just going to fail what are all of these
and I have all of this it's just a bunch
of lists of this plot cycle bullet
points this plot cycle bullet points
this plot cycle bullet points and then I
start in my outline to fold them
together into sections of the book uh
looking to have some big moment be a
demarcation of the end of a part and the
beginning of another part either some
big complication has happened or some
major step has been achieved along the
way and I start just interweaving these
in my outline to help me see this is
what the book is going to be it's going
to have this sense of progress on these
and there's going to be many um
information plot and I want to make sure
I don't lose it so we're going to make a
point happen here and then I build
chapters out of that as I write you
wouldn't go to my outline and be like
here's chapter one here's chapter two
chapter 3 you will generally have all of
these things moved into order in a giant
list of bullet points with plot headings
above explaining what each of them is
trying to do kind of in paragraph form
um and uh usually we can we put up an
outline one of my old ones I think we
have the Skyward outline um that you can
see and the thing about this I generally
work with them so you might go to
Skyward outline and have it be numbered
as chapters I'm sometimes numbering them
as I'm writing they are not numbered as
I make the outline but you're it after
I'm done with it and the book is done um
and so all of this it gets exponentially
more complicated the more characters you
add um be aware of that uh it's pretty
easy to write a one Viewpoint narrative
in a 100,000 words even using all the
World building and things I like to do
really hard to do too if they're
involved in the same exact plot you can
do it you me and the nightmare painters
is a two um but they're both in the same
plot if you're going to put two people
on different planet suddenly you know
it's it's it starts to magnify and it
can be more than a doubling effect
depending on uh on how much you're doing
there so um yeah what program do you use
for building your outling uh I use
Microsoft Word for building my outlines
yep I just use the document map and
Microsoft Word uh I'm old school give me
a piece of paper uh in a notebook in the
old days I would make them in a piece in
a notebook uh nowadays it's mic soft
word I know a lot of people like that
screenwriting one um what's it called uh
what's that scer scrier people really
like scrier um and I know a lot of
people that's handy for I do use an
internal Wiki that's just a local Wiki
for my team that handles all of the
World building they I make an outline I
write my book I hand the finished book
to them and they put it on in the wiki
so I can reference it later on uh I
don't have to do that anymore it's so
nice yeah so all right yeah kind linking
F do you like make your own Maps or do
you just like PA that off does he just
draw those yeah it uh do I make my own
Maps um so it depends on the book and
how relevant the spacing uh is so for
instance in Mporn I didn't generally
have Maps it's taking place in one city
and I knew that I'm like well this place
this has to be this far apart from this
other one when I wrote the original
draft of wave of Kings I I handrew one
out cuz I knew I'm like I have to know
how far it is from here to here um you
know one of the things they'll get you
for on the internet and rightly so is if
you have armies teleport around um so do
yourself a service have a map for scale
if you're going to be moving armies uh
you really want to have that ver
similitude of realism you can cut some
Corners with magic but they should be
established rules for your magic system
uh I can get away with a lot in storm
light because
the armies don't have to forage they can
carry with them the ability in a small
cart of something to make large amounts
of food um they don't have to worry
about water they you will have plenty of
water uh in RAR too much um right so
there are things that I can do that make
the movement of armies a lot easier for
me um so that the logistics uh I don't
have to run supply lines nearly as much
and things like that but depends on what
type of story you're telling so uh yeah
you follow up quick follow yeah are you
excited for Civ am I excited for civ7
yes um I'm excited for C7 because it
might solve one of the biggest problems
in forx history which is it might make
me actually finish a game right if you
played forx it's like well I feel like
I'm done now I've played this for you
know like and then you start a new one
uh they look like they're looking at
that I am worried that they will too
much abandon their coolest feature from
six which was the adjacencies and the
planning it was so much fun in six to
sit down and plan your Empire and then
build it step by step feels like writing
a book we're like finally I get to place
this thing here and get this city here
and I worry there won't be as much cool
planning and that was my favorite part
of six so uh no more six7 questions uh
we'll work over here for a while yeah
what advice do you have for like
foreshadowing and internal consistency
for Discovery okay foreshadowing
internal consistency for Discovery
writers fix it and
post um that's a joke but seriously
foreshadowing is actually one of the
very easiest things to fix in revision
you can turn up or down a foreshadowing
knob super easily um and so as a
discovery writer you can put that all in
uh in fact I would recommend you finish
your book you know what it's all about
uh you know need to foreshadow say well
now I'm going to use this thing Brandon
talked about and be like all right to in
order to earn this ending I need this
this and this I'm going to have a list
of those as I go through my revision or
I'm just going to go to the chapter and
see put this in here construct a scene
that does this um or if your
foreshadowing was too much you're like
well I need a red herring uh I'll insert
a red herring a little harder than
turning up foreshadowing turning it up
is easier than turning it down but it's
so easy to add for shadowing and tweak
that uh one of the things that I rely on
early readers the most for is where
figuring out where they're guessing my
plot twists and I look for kind of a
distribution I don't usually want plot
twists that nobody
guesses this is where my personal
threshold is I feel like if you can't
possibly have guessed it it's not really
a a cool plot twist it can be a
complication they can there can be
complications nobody guesses that's
totally fine and you have that all the
time but if what I actually want is a
Twist if there's a reveal that is
foreshadowed and nobody's able to get it
then I might have done the wrong thing
like um I want most people to not get it
until like the page or the paragraph
before the reveal that's where I'm
wanting it in order to get that some
people are going to guess it after act
one or in some cases and book one for
book five but if you but there's no
getting around that unless you make the
twist so obscure that nobody gets them
however if everybody is getting it in
act one then either I need to dial back
on my fores shattering or I need to make
it not a surprise
Dune gets away with no
surprises um this is the ER example of
that uh but hitch talk would do this too
um
there is a difference between a Twist
and suspense right of like if you know
there's a bomb somewhere and the
characters don't you can create suspense
out of that if you know a certain
character is a traitor and the
characters don't Dune gets a lot of
mileage out of that um it doesn't hide
this from you and it works really well
you can do that if you're like wow
everyone's guessing this why don't I
just lean into it and make it so that
the characters don't have the
information we have because we can see
through the villain eyes and then make
sure your characters don't feel dumb but
otherwise there you go so the answer
really is fix it in revisions okay I'm
going to go over here and then I'm going
to get this side because I've been
ignoring them on the subject of twists
yes some stories seem to have twists
that come out of shock yes
there the true answer is yes there is I
don't like them very much as an artistic
choice but there is there is value to
them um and some usually these are
better as
complications right um you know spoiler
for Game of Thrones but somebody gets
beheaded that no other fantasy book at
the time would have beheaded in Game of
Thrones and then he does it again in a
later book this built the series for uh
for people who like that the shock value
works in those books because he is
trying to do the War of the Roses a real
historical sort of time period um in
fact I believe westros is like Great
Britain turned upside down the P right
with um with like Ireland stapled on top
of it or something um like he was very
he's a medievalist he's like yeah that's
what it is this is the War of the Roses
with a with a flavor of fantasy and I
want to explore the brutality of being a
ruler in the Medieval Era um and so if
the story's theme is exploring the
brutality of living in the middle evil
era than having people die in ways that
normal fantasy stories wouldn't gains a
lot of shock value uh and that enhances
the storytelling because it makes it
like well who's going to be next No One
Is Safe um problem is it's hard to have
a long running series with sympathetic
characters if you just keep doing that
and so even George had to you know pull
pull back um which is one of the big
criticisms of the series it's a it's a
natural kind of necessity to the story
he was telling I think they will like
his fans don't actually want him to kill
everybody
um but I don't know uh
regardless um yeah
so is there value yes make sure the
value is in watching the characters
respond to something completely
unexpected and letting that develop your
story in interesting directions rather
than doing it just to shock the reader
because again shocking the reader is not
hard it takes no skill um like anyone
can do it you just say page 100 and they
got together and lived happily ever
after and then there's 300 blank pages
after that that's a Twist anyone could
do that uh does not take any skill um so
make sure that that even the one you're
doing primarily for shock value is done
in such a way that it enhances the
themes the characters the plot in a way
that works for the narrative that you're
telling and be careful of about it be
aware that
statistically this hurts me this hurts
me
statistically people enjoy stories more
if they know the twists ahead of
time this has been researched over and
over and over again with lots of
different test audiences that people
they sit them down and say I'm going to
spoil this for you now watch it they
consistently rate the story higher if
they've been
spoiled doesn't that hurt doesn't that
absolutely hurt um this is where I
started to learn to just not mind if
certain people who know what makes them
engage with fiction flip to the end of
the book to make to see who's alive and
dead and usually what happens is the car
the reader can enjoy the story certain
uh psychologies enjoy it better because
they don't have to stress if their
favorite character dies or not so
therefore they can actually engage with
the narrative and really come to like it
yeah you guys are all muttering about
this you're like I can't believe people
they're the
worst oh man readers if only we could
have books without them
um
yeah so keep that in mind because what
that means
is a well foreshadowed twist that people
spot
yes it but still really like is going to
be an imort more likely to be an
immortal book A book that changes
because beta
readers understood figured it out too
much or even worse people read the first
book figured out where you're going so
you absolutely re uh change the second
book so all your for shadowing the first
book doesn't work anymore those books
tend to be on shaky grounds by the ones
that authors that I've studied who I
know have done it and it in the long run
I think has been detrimental to the
series so there's a little bit of a
couple diet tribes on that all right I'm
going to work my way this way I'll go
here and then we'll look over here we'll
go here and then here and then I'll ask
in that one okay so we've mentioned
foreshadowing a bunch how would you go
about giving foreshadowing tips to
someone who says I know what I need to
foreshadow but I'm struggling to do it
effectively okay uh you know what you
need to foreshadow you're struggling to
do it effectively all right couple of
tips readers will follow a couple of
things number one genre and narrative
tropes if they think they have figured
it
out then you can surprise them with
something else okay and you can help
them lean into that so you're
foreshadowing if you're having trouble
making it so that people don't see but
you want to hide in plain sight you can
see what they expect and then you can
start playing with it all right um
understand that generally if you're
really Bare Bones you can do the rule of
three mention something three times
before it's important and
relevant okay um if readers were like
this it fell out of
nowhere your readers will follow the
character's attention what the
characters notice and say wow that's
important the readers will notice and
say wow that's important when the the so
you can focus reader attention with
character attention and this works for
Side characters too right often one of
the best ways to show that a character
is a you know is a good person is not to
have them be like yeah I'm a good
person I I I I I I teach classes for for
the University when I don't have to
instead you're all laughing
um instead having someone else
say say Brandon is awesome is awesome
see it I'm I'm joking but one of the
reasons why the beginning of Stormlight
I do not show chapter one from kaladin's
Viewpoint is because kaledin in chapter
one is just too dang awesome and if
you're in his Viewpoint it might be too
much and it might feel like I tired of
this guy he's too cool showing him from
the eyes of someone else who he
rescues changes all of that their
attention is on him and then you're like
I love this guy he came and saved this
little kid he didn't need to save
Through The Eyes of the kid's Viewpoint
and he can do all the awesome stuff
without it being as um as over the top
as it might be from his Viewpoint and
then you know you work in a few flaws
you work in um some some backstory stuff
and and there's a lot going on there but
that I deliberately chose that it adds
to the learning curve because it's a
Viewpoint that is not the main character
viewpoint but I thought the tradeoff was
uh good there because it let me do
things so foreshadowing wise watch what
your characters are doing what they're
paying attention to and if you need more
foreshadowing you can go with the old
standby characters like it does does not
make any sense at
all that such and such happened to the
other characters do you does that now my
my wrong is that odd and other
characters like now that you mention it
it makes absolutely no sense in our
magic system um I'm sure I trust the
author though I'm sure it'll make sense
eventually like yeah yeah it probably
will um and then later on they're like
this still hasn't made sense and then
later on they're like oh wow that's why
uh I've just pulled the curtain back
you're going to read missor different
now yeah
um why are there only 10 medals when 16
seems like there would be there's
there's only half of a chart in the back
of the book I don't know just one of
those things I'm not 16 medals why would
there be all right yeah sorry okay all
right you got a question U what are your
tips to avoid a decline in quality after
like a midpoint climax or the ending
climax of a book one so book two how do
you avoid uh a decline in quality after
you've had just an awesome climax in the
middle of book one or book one moving to
book two this is hard right sometimes it
just sings uh and then you're like well
that was a great book how do I follow
that up uh that's a problem for future
you
make that first book as cool as it can
be the midpoint climax is more of a more
of an issue um generally when I've had
this there's a couple of things that
I've done in some cases I'm like can
that be the endpoint climax instead it
is working so well can I move it I
actually have done that before uh
sometimes I'll be like well I just need
to step up be a man uh um sing a Donnie
Osman song We referenc Mulan we have to
do again um and make the ending even
cooler and that means for me it could
take a few weeks of rebuilding plot
lines um something that I was just
working on I'm like wow this protag this
this I have like a uh a narrative and a
plot I'm like this one is going to be
awesome it is so cool and I looked at
the other Viewpoint and I'm like
everyone's going to want to skip this
one take get to this one I'm like all
right we're going to take a few weeks
and we're going to make that second
Viewpoint use every tool I can to up the
how interesting and engaging that
Viewpoint is going to be so that the
balance really is uh is working once in
a while I just don't
care um this is the Tres of the emerald
sea problem right TR the best climax
happens right at the 3/4 mark and it
couldn't really be moved because the
emotional and narrative climax happens
at the end but like the best plot climax
happens at the 3/4 Mark and I just
decided this is a quirk of this book
right uh you're going to get these two
climaxes and one is going to a little
bit overshadow the other one um and
that's fine I just you know I played
with changing it around I played with
other things and I felt like it was the
right narrative even though it has that
Quirk to it um so sometimes you just do
that so any of the three I think are
viable the second one is the one that
you want to try to practice the most
though yeah go ahead how important do
you think it is to have the climax like
I mean like you kind of you kind of said
that but like personally I kind of like
there to be a little bit longer
resolution than I feel like it's typical
of books but is that weird of me so you
like to have resolution climaxes they're
longer than they're typical readers tend
to actually like that so you're probably
fine it depends on the type of story
you're telling right I wouldn't suggest
that your flash fiction piece have a
5000w Koda um right uh but at the same
time going a little longer at the end
like let's be honest nobody is
skipping um The Return of the King
because it has a bit of an extra ending
and a bit of an extra ending and in the
book and even B right no one is skipping
the dark night because it has three
endings lingering right and it really
does those are like both movies that uh
like are touted is among the best and
they both really Linger on their endings
you'll probably be fine may you be so
skilled that when you get to the end no
one cares that you're self-indulging a
little in the ending because they
secretly love it even though it's
breaking story structure because they
just loved being in your story so much
that they want you to keep going okay so
there you are all right back here um if
we're starting of like in the status quo
and like the Ordinary World before we
get to the ins makit how do you put
through what are the ways they yeah okay
this is an excellent question this is
something that we're confronted by a ton
you're starting in the Ordinary World
you want to hook the reader you want to
give the right promises what do you do
so one answer is the mul Mulan answer
you focus on what is cool about this
character and show them doing something
really interesting um to solve a problem
that it they're never going to solve the
problem the same way but they are going
to use those same skills later on and a
lot of stories do a really good job with
this uh they spend that early time just
making you really interested in how the
character problem solves or how who they
are so that when you get shaken out of
that you know you're pulled in um
another way to do it is to have the
little the little spark of magic in
there even if it's not you know you're
you're not yet going on your big
adventure but remember like Harry Potter
starts with Hagrid turning off lights
with a with with you know or is it it's
Dumbledore Dumbledore pulling the lights
and Hagrid riding on a bike right um
like even if you discount the opening PR
log to Wheel of Time which Tred to get
around this problem Rand only spends one
chapter before real weird stuff starts
happening right um a lot of books that
like Wheel of Time people like are kind
of historic it's historically it's it's
90s fantasy written in the 80s it has
kind of that slower opening but that's
not as Slow Burn as uh as people
remember it being it's just compared to
now so you can get you can do one
chapter and then have the spark or even
a couple chapters but sometimes you can
work that in um just giving us something
to latch on to that makes the character
and situation interesting to us that
then is applicable in some way to the
rest of the story that's what you're
trying to figure out how to do um and
you'll you'll find lots of uh stories
that what they do is even if they don't
do the fantasy prologue this is really
common in middle grade it's like
character um was standing there trying
to figure out how their dog disappeared
why did their dog disappear or why is
there dirt gently does this why is there
um a sofa lodged in the stairwell uh
when it couldn't by the laws of physics
get there they're pondering some weird
thing and then they go to mundane life
at school but the weird things just keep
happening and then boom we're you know
fullon fantasy you see that a ton too
okay um all right we're going to go here
but then uh you've already gotten one so
I need to let the um the peanut gallery
have some more questions so I'm going to
let you do and then for the last like
few minutes we'll let you guys cuz I'm
I'm predisposed to point the people
whose hands are in my face the most not
that I mind no no you're okay you're
okay I was gonna I wanted to let you
know so I I would get to you but let's
go over here yeah how do you make
satisfy not character fail
theal okay characters fail the goal
they've been pursuing how do you make it
satisfying and not feel like total
ripoff if they completely
fail um
well some of the best stories ever do
this it depends on a couple of factors
number one it's a very big difference if
the reader knows another installment is
coming right Empire Strikes Back is a
very different would be a very different
movie if Lucas said I'm telling two
stories and this is the end right um
knowing that something is coming will
help and if you're just going to have it
just be completely failure at the end
you usually um you want either the
reader to be like you know what that's
what they deserve that's the little more
literary fiction version of it right
everything goes wrong it's probably what
they deserved right um like Butch
casting a Sundance Kid getting mowed
down it's like well you know guys I love
you but you you you had this coming
right um You don't get to live happily
ever after you're going to get gunned
down
um right like those sorts of stories can
be really satisfying if the reader like
yes it's not what the characters wanted
but it's what the cosmos wanted it's the
right answer that they can't have what
they want and particular if you spend
the story showing them self-destructive
or things if it is they're just not
strong enough then it can work very well
that be like we just weren't strong
enough if it's bittersweet something is
accomplished but a lot of things weren't
right like like the fact um that you
Pandora's box right the fact that at the
end of the uh Fellowship of the Ring Sam
goes anyway and you get that little
Victory right everything's gone wrong
but Sam goes anyway you've got this just
like little glimmer and it also is a
promise right uh where you're like okay
you know the promise of the Ring would
corupt everyone happened um but Sam's
still there so you know you can find a
lot lot of ways to navigate this and it
really depends on what type of story
you're telling and what how you want the
like what's the emotional disposition
you want do you want the emotional
disposition to be wow I can't believe
they failed I sure hope that they pull
it out next time or is it you know quot
you had this
coming uh and I watched your steady
downfall and destruction and yeah that's
what's supposed to happen I'm sorry I
really like you but you know you deserve
this uh those are two different stories
entirely and depends on what you're
trying to do all right five minutes left
anyone in the peanut gallery got a
question yeah go
ahead oh memory loss plot lines they're
they're so fun but they're so hard right
um if you haven't read one of these
project Hail Mary is an amazing one um
yeah it's really really good um and uh
so these stories tend to work by raising
questions and then answering them with
little bits uh a lot of the things that
make these stories tend to work is small
problems that can be fixed right and
while you're fixing it you discover some
things so it's like all right I am going
to you know I'm in the bottom of the
ocean I wake up and my I'm in like a
habitat and the windows are cracked I
need to pack the windows and so in the
patching of the windows they discover
some things right and then all right
what's my next problem all right then
they discover a little bit more so if
there're you really rely in these
stories on problem solving problem
solving is kind of key to keeping us
engaged and because they don't know
what's going on they don't know the
capital P plot you have to give them
really engaging little PE plots that
they can solve really fast as you start
to introduce the capital P plot and
usually you have their memory come back
uh often in flashbacks to show how they
got there to the point that then by the
time you're ready with capital P plot
you have gotten them there with all
these little events the the reader being
gotten the reader there and
understanding what's going on that's the
best I can give you uh study some of the
really good ones uh and you'll see
you'll see how they do it yeah all right
panut gallery on the way back uh I I'll
let you go next you're in the middle P
gy back there and then you okay yeah how
do you decide between a different PL IDE
how do I decide between a bunch of
different plot ideas um it's just a Vib
thing when I finish a book and and I
have the time to write another one I
just go with the vibe of whatever is
most exciting to me at that point or
what I have a deadline
for may you be so
lucky yeah what are some things you can
ask like your beta readers or
thoughts stats asking that give you good
indicators on okay what are things you
can ask your beta readers that give you
good indicators on uh whether your
plot's working uh I mean it's the so
here's the thing um writing groups are
bad with pacing beta readers tend to be
good right writing groups are going to
be reading this in chunks be careful
about changing pacing too much based on
uh on writing groups beta readers you
can just have them say where are you
bored that's really what you want to
know um where are you feeling like you
want to put the book
down where is your are you you know
where are you being pulled through and
where does it feel like you're just not
as interested you're going to have some
of those
scenes that you know you're going to
have your vegetables but there is a
there's a there there's lots of famous
adages about this like you know uh how
do you make a book better you just take
out the parts people don't like right or
how do how do you make a great book you
write only scenes that are good um there
is something to some of these Ates which
is like you can look at those scenes and
you can be like how can I get this
information across that's happening in
here in a more interesting way more
interesting than try to avoid where you
can two people walk down a hallway and
they Converse and shot reverse shot
right stay away from the prequel
trilogies method of
exposition there are so many
I'm walking down the hallway I stop and
I say mace what do you think about this
blah blah blah blah blah blah walk down
the hallway blah blah blah blah blah
blah right like you're going to have
some of those you're going to have
people having uh but even if you have
them having supper and you can have like
something that's going on with the
dinner like the soup like I try to
construct the scene so there's a little
more motion a little more happening and
a little bit of problem solving even in
that scene if you run into them all
right we're out of time mole next week
Brandon mole is going to come um and so
enjoy that and I'll see you in two weeks